TIMOTHY FEENEY

Brookline, Massachusetts, United States

thefeeney.netlify.com @TFeend tpfeeney@gmail.com timothy.feeney@bmc.org tfeeney@bmj.com

BRIEF PERSONAL STATEMENT

My name is Tim and I am a Post Doctoral Fellow in the Department of Surgery at Boston University/Boston Medical Center. I have an MD and clinical training in general surgery, a masters in clinical biochemistry, and an MPH with focus on epidemiology and bio-statistics. My clinical interests are Acute Care/Trauma surgery and Critical Care. My research interests are in clinical epidemiology and the application of advanced epidemiological methods to observational studies to better understand bias an obtain causal inferences. I am currently investigating the impact of language on post-operative outcomes, differences in palliative care utilization, and how to improve follow up of incidentally identified lesions of the adrenal gland.

My interests outside of science and math involve my family (wife and daughter), visiting museums, reading and finding great bargains on used books, and SCUBA diving on deep wrecks and inside caves. I have also spent a large chunk of my life as a firefighter and an EMT, which will always hold a place in my heart.

CURRENT POSITION(S)

Post Doctoral Research Fellow

11/2017-Present

Dept. of Surgery–Boston University/Boston Medical Center, Boston MA.

Clinical Epidemiology and Bio-statistics Researcher, Project Supervisor

Designed, implemented, and analyzed longitudinal prospective quality improvement initiative

Performed multiple large observational database studies using both Frequentist and Bayesian methods

Study design and analysis consulting

Associate Research Editor

04/2019-Present

The BMJ.

Editorial work involving decisions regarding publication in The BMJ.

EDUCATION

Master of Public Health

May 2017

Harvard University T.H Chan School of Public Health, Boston MA.

Quantitative Methods; focus on Epidemiology and Biostatistics

Doctor of Medicine May 2014

University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore MD.

Master of Science May 2012

University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore MD.

Medical Biochemistry

Bachelor of Science/Bachelor of Arts

May 2008

7/2015-6/2016

University of Maryland, College Park, College Park MD.

BS: Molecular Biology; cum laude

BA: Government and Politics; magna cum laude

High Honors in Chemistry and Biochemsitry

Valedictorian Speaker for College of Chemical and Life Sciences Commencement

CLINICAL TRAINING

Tufts Medical Center, Boston, MA

Residency, PGY2, General Surgery

Stamford Hospital, Stamford, CT 7/2014-6/2015

Internship, General Surgery

First Authored

- **Feeney, Timothy**, Michael Cassidy, Yorghos Tripodis, David McAneny, Maureen Kavanah, Teviah Sachs, Jennifer F. Tseng, and Frederick Thurston Drake. "Association of Primary Language with Outcomes After Operations Typically Performed to Treat Cancer: Analysis of a Statewide Database". In: *Annals of Surgical Oncology* (June 11, 2019). DOI: 10.1245/s10434-019-07484-8.
- **Feeney, Timothy** et al. "Evaluation of Incidental Adrenal Masses at a Tertiary Referral and Trauma Center". In: Surgery (Oct. 2019). DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.surg.2019.07.034.
- Feeney, Timothy, Sabrina Elena Sanchez, Yorghos Tripodis, Tejal Sudhirkumar Brahmbhatt, Robert Schulze, Peter Burke, Tracey Dechert, and Frederick Thurston Drake. "The Association of Primary Language With Emergency General Surgery Outcomes Using a Statewide Database". In: *Journal of Surgical Research* 244 (Dec. 2019), pp. 484–491. DOI: 10.1016/j.jss.2019.06.082.
- Feeney, Timothy, Manuel Castillo-Angeles, John W. Scott, Stephanie L. Nitzschke, Ali Salim, Adil H. Haider, and Joaquim M. Havens. "The Independent Effect of Emergency General Surgery on Outcomes Varies Depending on Case Type: A NSQIP Outcomes Study". In: *The American Journal of Surgery* 216.5 (Nov. 2018), pp. 856–862. DOI: 10.1016/j.amjsurg.2018.03.006.
- Feeney, Timothy, Lori Lyn Price, Lilian Chen, Roger Graham, and Abhishek Chatterjee. "Resident and Fellow Participation in Thyroid and Parathyroid Surgery: An ACS-NSQIP Clinical Outcomes Analysis". In: *Journal of Surgical Research* 220 (Dec. 2017), pp. 346–352. DOI: 10.1016/j.jss.2017.07.030.

Co-Authored

- Castillo-Angeles, Manuel, Tarsicio Uribe-Leitz, Molly Jarman, Ginger Jin, **Feeney, Timothy**, Ali Salim, and Joaquim M. Havens. "Transferred Emergency General Surgery Patients Are at Increased Risk of Death: A NSQIP Propensity Score Matched Analysis". In: *Journal of the American College of Surgeons* (Jan. 2019). DOI: 10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2019.01.014.
- Nguyen, Minh-Thuy, **Feeney, Timothy**, Chanmin Kim, F. Thurston Drake, Suzanne E. Mitchell, Magdalena Bednarczyk, and Sabrina E. Sanchez. "Differential Utilization of Palliative Care Consultation Between Medical and Surgical Services". In: *American Journal of Hospice and Palliative Medicine* (Aug. 6, 2019), p. 104990911986790. DOI: 10.1177/1049909119867904.
- Drake, Frederick Thurston et al. "Laparoscopic Adrenalectomy for Metastatic Disease: Retrospective Cohort with Long-Term, Comprehensive Follow-Up". In: Surgery (Dec. 2018). DOI: 10.1016/j.surg.2018.11.008.
- Ghuman, Amandeep, S.W. de Jonge, Simon D. Dryden, **Feeney, Timothy**, Daniel H. Buitrago, and P. Terry Phang. "Prophylactic Use of Alpha-1 Adrenergic Blocking Agents for Prevention of Postoperative Urinary Retention: A Review & Meta-Analysis of Randomized Clinical Trials". In: *The American Journal of Surgery* 215.5 (May 2018), pp. 973–979. DOI: 10.1016/j.amjsurg.2018.01.015.
- Jang, Yoon J., Abigail L. LaBella, **Feeney, Timothy** P., Nancy Braverman, Mendel Tuchman, Hiroki Morizono, Nicholas Ah Mew, and Ljubica Caldovic. "Disease-Causing Mutations in the Promoter and Enhancer of the Ornithine Transcarbamylase Gene". In: *Human Mutation* 39.4 (Apr. 2018), pp. 527–536. DOI: 10.1002/humu. 23394.
- Laser, Adriana et al. "Long-Term Follow-up of Blunt Cerebrovascular Injuries: Does Time Heal All Wounds?" In: Journal of Trauma and Acute Care Surgery 81.6 (Dec. 2016), pp. 1063–1069. DOI: 10.1097/TA.000000000001223.
- Lauerman, Margaret H. et al. "Lethal Now or Lethal Later: The Natural History of Grade 4 Blunt Cerebrovascular Injury". In: *Journal of Trauma and Acute Care Surgery* 78.6 (June 2015), pp. 1071–1075. DOI: 10.1097/TA. 000000000000654.

- Pho, Nam, Dino R C Magri, Fernando F Redigolo, **Feeney, Timothy**, and CJ Patel. "Data Transfer in a Science DMZ Using SDN with Applications for Precision Medicine in Cloud and High-Performance Computing". In: (2015), p. 4.
- LaBella, Abigail Leavitt, **Feeney, Timothy**, Sandra Heibel, Mendel Tuchman, and Ljubica Caldovic. "Analysis of Urea Cycle Gene Transcription Regulation Using Bioinformatic Software and Patient Sequences". In: *The FASEB Journal* 25 (1_supplement 2011), pp. 564.8–564.8. DOI: 10.1096/fasebj.25.1_supplement.564.8.
- LaBella, Abigail Leavitt, **Feeney, Timothy**, Sandra Kirsch Heibel, Mendel Tuchman, and Ljubica Caldovic. "Comprehensive Bioinformatic Analysis of Urea Cycle Gene Transcription Regulation Using Cis-Element over Representation (CLOVER) Software and Patient Sequences to Identify Disease Causing Mutations". In: *Molecular Genetics and Metabolism*. Vol. 102. 2011, pp. 297–297.

PRESENTATIONS

Podium

- A Simplified Method to Account for Multiple Case Adjustment in Regression Modeling. 15th Annual Academic Surgical Congress Podium Presentation. Orlando, Florida, Feb. 2020.
- Challenges in the Management of Adrenal Incidentalomas: One Year at an Urban Level I Trauma Center. 14th Annual Academic Surgical Congress Oral Presentation. Houston TX, Feb. 2019.
- The Effect of Primary Language on Emergency General Surgery Outcomes: A Statewide Database Study. 14th Annual Academic Surgical Congress Oral Presentation. Houston, TX, Feb. 2019.
- Non-English Language and Outcomes in Emergency General Surgery. Oral Presentation at Massachusetts State American College of Surgeons Committee on Trauma. Worcester MA, 2018.
- The Effect of Trainee Involvement on Patient Outcomes in General Surgery Cases Over Time. 13th Annual Academic Surgical Congress Oral Presentation. Jacksonville FL, Jan. 2018.
- Resident and Fellow Participation in Thyroid and Parathyroid Surgery: An American College of Surgeons NSQIP Clinical Outcomes Analysis. 63rd Annual New England Surgical Society Annual Meeting Oral Presentation. Boston MA, Sept. 2016.
- Hemoperitoneum Due to Traumatic Avulsion of a Single Leiomyoma Following a Motor Vehicle Collision. Oral Presentation at The Connecticut American College of Surgeons Annual Meeting, New Haven, CT, 2014.
- Through the Looking Glass: Telemedicine as a Potential Cure for the Community Intensivist Shortage. Paper Presented at University of Maryland School of Medicine Clinical Capstone Research Project Finalist Presentation Symposium, Baltimore MD. 2014.
- Investigation of miRNA-Directed Control of LDL Receptor Expression. 32nd Annual UMSOM Medical Student Research Day Oral Presentation. Baltimore, MD, 2009.
- Mutations in an Ornithine Transcarbamylase Regulatory Region as a Possible Cause for Reduced Expression in Patients with Ornithine Transcarbamylase Deficiency. Honors Thesis Defense. 2008.

Poster

- **Timothy Feeney**, Stephanie Vaughn, Jacob Nudel, Donald T Hess, Brian J Carmine, Cullen O Carter, Luise I Pernar, and Frederick Thurston Drake. "Limited English Proficiency Is Not Associated with Worse Outcomes after Bariatric Surgery." Dec. 7, 2019.
- **Timothy Feeney**, M Cassidy, D McAneny, M Kavanah, T Sachs, JF Tseng, and FT Drake. "Effect of Limited English Proficienty on Outcomes Following Cancer Operations". 2018.

- **Timothy Feeney** et al. "Epidemiology of Incidental Adrenal Masses at an Urban Tertiary Referral and Trauma Center". 2018.
- **Timothy Feeney**, M Cassidy, Y Tripodis, D McAneny, M Kavanah, T Sachs, JF Tseng, and FT Drake. "The Effect of Primary Language on Outcomes Following Cancer Operations Using a Statewide Database". 2018.
- **Timothy Feeney**, M Castillo Angeles, S Nitzschke, A Salim, A Haider, and J Havens. "Morbidity and Mortality of Emergency General Surgery Based on National Burden". 2017.

Timothy Feeney, H Morizono, and L Caldovic. "Genetic Regulation of OTC in the Urea Cycle". 2009.

Co-Authored

- Min-Thuy Nguyen, **Timothy Feeney**, Chanmin Kim, Frederick Thurston Drake, S.E Mitchell, M Bednarczyk, and Sabrina E. Sanchez. "Race as a Determinant of Palliative Care Consultation at a Safety-Net Urban Hospital". Feb. 4, 2020.
- Frederick Godley, **Timothy Feeney**, Christine Park, Michael Cassidy, Teviah E Sachs, David McAneny, Jennifer F Tseng, and Frederick Thurston Drake. "The Association of Primary Language with Outcomes after Cancer Operations at a Single Tertiary Referral Center and Safety Net Hospital." Sept. 13, 2019.
- Linda Salazar, **Timothy Feeney**, Chelsea Vigna, Avneesh Gupta, Philip Knapp, and F. Thurson Drake. "Improving Communication and Evaluation of Incidental Adrenal Findings". Nov. 12, 2019.
- Susanna W de Geus, Kurt S. Shultz, **Timothy Feeney**, Sing Chau Ng, Frederick Thurston Drake, David McAneny, Jennifer F Tseng, and Teviah E. Sachs. "Surgical and Oncologic Outcomes of Open Versus Laparoscopic Distal Pancreatectomy in a Low-Volume Setting". Sept. 13, 2019.
- Emily Palmquist, **Timothy Feeney**, Abhishek Chatterjee, D. Nepomnayshy, and Lilian Chen. "Medical Student Perceptions Following Participation in a Surgical Boot Camp A Qualitative Analysis." Feb. 5, 2018.
- Manuel Castillo-Angeles, Tarsicio Uribe-Leitz, Molly Jarman, **Timothy Feeney**, Ali Salim, and Joaquim M Havens. "Transferred Emergency General Surgery Patients Are at Increased Risk of Death". Sept. 23, 2018.

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

2019 The association of limited English proficiency with outcomes after cancer operations; perspectives from a large database and single center study

Presented at: The Boston Medical Center Annual Mozden Visiting Professorship Conference

2019 Hierarchical/Multilevel Modeling: An Introduction

Presented at: BU Surgery Resident Research Seminar

2019 Conceptual Models for Regression Analysis in Observational Data: Confounding, Mediation, and Effect Modification

Presented at: BU Surgery Resident Research Seminar

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- 2019 MDEpiNet Executive Operations Committee
- 2019 Present: Society for Epidemiologic Research-Communications Committee

HONORS AND AWARDS

- 2018 Winner of the Annual MA ACS Committee on Trauma Resident/Fellow Paper Competition
- 2017 UC Berkeley Social Sciences Research Transparency and Reproducibility (BITSS-RT2) Scholarship
- 2016 Tufts Annual Resident Research Day Finalist
- 2014 Medical School Capstone Research Project Finalist
- 2014 Clinical Honors: Acute Care Surgery, Trauma Surgery, Anesthesia, and Community Medicine
- 2008 Cell Bio and Molecular Genetics Program Distinguished Graduating Student

2008 University of Maryland, College Park Senior Marshal

2005-2008 Distinguished Deans List

2007-2008 College of Chemical and Life Sciences Outstanding Student

STUDENT MENTORSHIP

Christine Park-BU Medical Student, Boston MA

2018-2019

Project: Association of Language with Operative Outcomes at a Tertiary Safety Net Hopsital-A Single Center Study Ouptut: Manuscript in preparation

Gus Godley-BU MD MBA Student, Boston MA

2018-2019

Project: The association of primary language with outcomes after cancer operations at a single tertiary referral center and safety net hospital.

Output: Podium Presentation at the American College of Surgeons 2019 Annual Meeting Poster Presentation at the New England Surgical Society 2019 Annual Meeting

Minh-Thuy Nguyen - BU Medical Student, Boston MA

2018-2019

Project:Disparities in the utilization of palliative care consultations

Output: Differential Utilization of Palliative Care Consultation between Medical and Surgical Services—manuscript published

Output: Patient-Level Factors Influencing Utilization of Palliative Care Consultation at a Safety-Net Urban Hospitalabstract submitted to 2020 Academic Surgical Congress

Andrea Alonso - BU Medical Student, Boston MA

2019

Project: Bariatric surgery and language outcomes

Project: Systematic Review of Language Discordance and Outcomes in Inpatient, Emergency, and Surgery Settings

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Resident Instructor, Boston MA

2014-2016

Taught medical students about general surgery and critical care

Math and Science Tutor, Baltimore MD

2008-2010

Tutoring high school students from disadvantaged Baltimore area schools

Course Instructor: Weill-Cornell Youth Scholars Program, New York NY

2008

Summer program to mentor less advantage underrepresented minority high school students in STEM

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant, College Park, MD

2006

Taught General Microbiology

PREVIOUS RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Brigham and Womens Hospital, Boston, MA

11/2016-11/2017

Post Graduate Researcher

Investigating surgical clinical outcomes using NSQIP database

Extensive use of SAS, R and Stata

Tufts Medical Center, Boston, MA

11/2015-05/2016

Resident Researcher

Investigating resident impact on surgical outcomes

R. Adams Cowley Shock Trauma Center, Baltimore, MD

11/2013-5/2014

Student Clinical Researcher

Evaluated outcomes of patients with blunt cerebrovascular injury

University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD

2009-2010

Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology

Researched miR10 and its role in Pediatric Leukemias

Techniques used: PCR, Real-time PCR, RNA extraction/isolation,

Cell Culture, Western Blotting, Agarose Gel extraction and electrophoresis,

bacterial cloning.

Undergraduate Research

Research on the Urea Cycle

Techniques used: PCR, PCR, Sanger Sequencing, Bioinformatics

(BLAST, CLUSTALW, alignment manipulation, Transfac database and

transcription factor binding site prediction modeling)

LEADERSHIP

2009-2010	Vice-President.	Medical	Student	Journal	Club
2000 2010	VICO I I COIGCIIO	modical	Duddelli	oourna	Ciuo

2009-2010 Research Vice-President, Infectious Disease Interest Group

2009-2011 Student Council Representative, UMSOM MD/PhD Student Council

2008 Site Manager and Program Coordinator, Weill-Cornell Youth Scholars Program

2007-2008 Student representative, UMD CFLS Deans Advisory Board

2003-2004 Apparatus Engineer, Community Volunteer Fire Co. No. 1

PREVIOUS SELECTED ACTIVITIES

2004-2007 I	${ m Firefighter}_{ m i}$	/EMT,	Bladensburg	Volunteer	Fire 1	Department,	PGFD
-------------	---------------------------	-------	-------------	-----------	--------	-------------	------

2002-2005 Firefighter, Community Volunteer Fire Company No. 1

2003-2005 Emergency Medical Technician, West Milford First Aid Squad

2010-2012 MSTP Advisory Board Student Representative

2009-2011 MSTP Curriculum Design Committee

2009-2012 Science Editor, Dual Decree MD/PhD Program Newsletter

2008-2010 Webmaster, UMD AMA Student Section

AD HOC PEER REVIEW

JAMA Surgery

Surgery

Society for Epidemiologic Research

Journal of Surgical Research

American Journal of Surgery

World Journal of Surgery

PREVIOUS GRANT EXPERIENCE

2007 Howard Hughes Medical Institute Undergraduate Research Fellowship

CERTIFICATIONS

2015 Advanced Trauma Life Support (ATLS)

2014 Fundamentals of Critical Care Support (FCCS)

Firefighter I, Firefighter II, Vehicle Rescue Technician, Ice Rescue Technician, Incident Management 100, 200, and 700, Federal Wildland Firefighter, AHA CPR, GUE Technical Trimix Diver, GUE Full Cave Diver, International Conflict Management

SKILLS AND INTERESTS

Skills

R Statistical Software: intermediate to advanced skill with data visualization, descriptive statistics, multivariable regression, and simulation

SAS statistical software :intermediate skill with data visualization, descriptive statistics, multivariable regression

STATA statistical software: intermediate to advanced skill with data visualization, descriptive statistics, multivariable regression

Python: basic skill LATEX: basic skill

Microsoft Office Suite: Advanced

Interests

Surgery (Trauma and Acute Care), Critical Care, Causal Inference, Bayesian Methods Biochemistry, Mathematical Biology, and Molecular Biology